Andre Kuhlenschmidt

Contact Information

1212 NE 198th St. Shoreline, WA, 98155 E-mail: andre.kuhlenschmidt@gmail.com

Phone: (812) 325-7906 Github: github.com/akuhlens WWW: akuhlens.github.io

Research Interests I am interested in designing, building, and maintaining compilers, runtime systems, type systems, and other tools that make it easier to produce quality software. My most recent work focuses on implementing ahead of time compilers targeting LLVM.

EDUCATION

Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana USA

Ph.D. Candidate ABD, Computer Science, May 2021

Advisor: Jeremy Siek

M.S., Computer Science, May 2016 May 2010

B.S., Business, Major: Entrepreneurship,

EXPERIENCE

Meta, Redmond, Washington USA

Software Engineer

December 2020 - April 2023

- Rated as Exceeding Exceptations for Individual Contributor Level 4 in 2022.
- Collaborated on the design of a programming language to make developing performant distributed applications easier.
- Started and led a research paper reading group to regularly review and discuss papers relevant to our compiler's design and implementation.
- Implemented algebraic datatypes, closures, mutuable arrays, local mutable variables, and a compiler backend targeting LLVM.

Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana USA

Graduate Research Assistant

January 2014 - December 2020

- Evaluated implementation techniques for sound gradually typed programming languages.
- Developed an ahead-of-time compiler called Grift.
- Measured performance improvements in compiler via benchmark experiments.
- Designed semantics that facilitate safety and efficiency.

Meta, Seattle, Washington USA

Software Engineering Ph.D. Intern

May 2019 - August 2019

- Extended Flow type checker to interactively edit code based on type inference.
- Extended Flow to automatically fix a class of errors that are caused by omitting type annotations.

Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana USA

Assistant Instructor

January 2016 - May 2018 August 2012 - May 2014

- Planned and constructed course materials and software for courses in programming language semantics and implementation, operating systems, and embedded systems.
- Instructed lab sessions of 5-30 students.
- Recognized as Assistant Instructor of the Year in 2018.

Conference Papers

Toward Efficient Gradual Typing for Structural Types via Coercions Andre Kuhlenschmidt, Deyaaeldeen Almahallawi, and Jeremy G. Siek. In Programming Language Design and Implementation 2019.

SKILLS

Languages: Racket, Scala, C, Haskell, Java, Python, Coq, C++ Tools and Platforms: Bash, Hg, Git, Make, Linux, Mac OS

Refereed Articles

An Efficient Compiler for the Gradually Typed Lambda Calculus Andre Kuhlenschmidt, Deyaaeldeen Almahallawi, Jeremy G. Siek. In Scheme and Functional Programming Workshop, 2018.

A Systematic Performance Evaluation of Gradually Typed Functions and References. Andre Kuhlenschmidt, Deyaaeldeen Almahallawi, Jeremy G. Siek. In Scripts to Programs Workshop, STOP, 2016.

Towards Absolutely Efficient Gradual Typing Andre Kuhlenschmidt, Deyaaeldeen Almahallawi, and Jeremy G. Siek. In Scripts to Programs Workshop, STOP, 2015.

OPEN SOURCE PROJECTS

Grift

May 2014 - December 2021

- Collaborator on an optimizing compiler for a gradually typed Lisp to native code.
- Utilizes *space-efficient coercions* to enforce soundness of the static type system, which results in a performance increase that is multiple orders of magnitude.

Professional Activities

IU Luddy Graduate Education Committee, Student RepresentativeJanuary 2018 - August 2020OOPSLA Artifact Evaluation CommitteeAugust 2018SPLASH Student Research Competition Program CommitteeAugust 2018